A Guide to the John Warwick Daniel Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
John Warwick Daniel Papers 1816-1936
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
158, 158-a, 3171, 5383, -a-, -b, -c, -d,-e
This collection consists of ca. 14,000 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The accessions that comprise this collection were purchased on seven different occasions: October 15, 1938 from Miss Warwick Daniel; and July 1956, July 8, 1957, December 1, 1957, July 7, 1958, September 27, 1958, and April 4, 1959 from Mrs. Glenna D. Anthony.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Warwick Daniel was born September 5, 1842, in Lynchburg, Virginia, the son of William and Sarah Anne (Warwick) Daniel. He attended private schools, Lynchburg College, and Gessner Harrison's classical school. With the outbreak of the Civil War, Daniel entered the Confederate Army in May, 1861, as a second lieutenant in the Provisional Army of Virginia and drill master in the Twenty-seventh Virginia Infantry, Stonewall Brigade. After the state army was dissolved, Daniel was appointed second lieutenant and afterward first lieutenant of Company A, Eleventh Virginia Infantry. He later became adjutant of the same regiment. Daniel raised his own company of cavalry and was elected captain in 1862, but the Conscription Act of 1862 forced the dissolution of volunteer groups such as his own and he returned to his former regiment. Daniel was wounded in the first Battle of Manassas and at Boonsboro, Maryland; however, the wound he received at the Battle of the Wilderness, May 6, 1864, after having been appointed major and chief of staff for General Jubal A. Early, ended Daniel's military career and crippled him for life.
After the war, Daniel studied law at the University of Virginia during the 1865-1866 session. He was admitted to the bar in 1866 and commenced practice in Lynchburg with his father. Daniel published two major legal works, one on attachments (1869) and another on negotiable instruments (1876).
Daniel entered politics soon after commencing his legal practice and held numerous offices during his lifetime. He served as a member of the Virginia House of Delegates from 1869 to 1872; in the state Senate from 1875 to 1881; as presidential elector on the Democratic ticket of Tilden and Hendricks in 1876; as a member of the Democratic national conventions in 1880, 1888, 1892, 1896, and 1900; was an unsuccessful Democratic candidate for governor in 1881; elected as a Democrat to the Forty-ninth Congress (March 4, 1885-March 3, 1887); and was elected in 1885 to the United States Senate, serving from 1887 until his death in Lynchburg on June 29, 1910.
In Virginia, Daniel opposed the Readjusters led by William Mahone; and, in 1881, was the unsuccessful Funder opponent of Readjuster William E. Cameron for governor. Daniel was also the leader of the free silver bloc in Virginia, delivering the keynote address on the currency question at the Democratic National Convention in 1896. At the 1901-1902 Virginia Constitutional Convention he served as chairman of the committee on the elective franchise, which successfully sought to disfranchise blacks. Daniel was highly acclaimed for his oratorical abilities; his address at the unveiling of the Robert E. Lee statue at Lexington, Virginia, in 1883, was especially admired. In the Senate Daniel gained a reputation as a spokesman for the anti-imperialist, anti-tariff, and free silver causes, as well as an advocate of sectional reconciliation and Southern equality.
Daniel married Julia Elizabeth Murrell of Lynchburg, Virginia, in 1869 and had five children: Caroline (Carrie) Daniel, Julia Daniel, John Warwick Daniel, Jr., Edward Murrell Daniel and William P. Daniel
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains correspondence of three generations of the Daniel family. The earliest, 1816-1825, is between William Daniel, his wife Margaret Baldwin Daniel, and their children, chiefly regarding family matters. From 1826-1845 Sarah Warwick Daniel and William Daniel, Jr. are the main correspondents. There is some discussion of Daniel's law practice, but most concerns the family.
The papers of John Warwick Daniel constitute the bulk of the collection. Civil War letters of Daniel and W.J. Kincheloe describe campaigns and battles, including Cedar Mountain, Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville, Gettysburg, Rappahannock Bridge, The Wilderness, Spotsylvania, and the North Anna River. Several letters from prisoners of war to E.S. Halsey appeal for aid.
Daniel's postwar correspondence ranges through his student days at U.Va., his political career in the Virginia State Legislature and the U.S. House, and his 23 years in the U.S. Senate. Much of the correspondence discusses family matters with his father, sister Sallie Warwick Daniel Halsey, wife Julia Elizabeth Murrell Daniel, and children Caroline Daniel, John Warwick Daniel, Jr., and Edward M. Daniel.
Other correspondence with many prominent political figures praises Daniel's famous oration on Robert E. Lee (extant) at the dedication of the Lee statue in Lexington, Va.; congratulates him on his election to the Senate; requests patronage; and discusses such issues as funderism, free silver and William Jennings Bryan, the Virginia Constitutional Convention of 1901, the Civil War, particularly Daniel's vindication of Jubal Early, and Lee, and Virginia artillery units.
The collection also contains Daniel's U.Va. student notebook; a legal notebook; two books of miscellaneous quotations; diaries from 1903-1907; an 1831 autograph album; and a diary, 1901, describing personal and political activities, including his attendance at the meetings of the Senate Finance and Foreign Relations Committees.
Topics in a large series of speeches and research notes include the South, Southern Democrats, territorial expansion in the Spanish-American War, the Hawaiian Revolution, taxes, tariffs, and the Readjustor movement. Political papers, 1877-1904, discuss the bribing of black voters, 1879; the Virginia-West Virginia debt controversy; and the 1896 presidential election. Legal papers, 1873-1909, contain notes and drafts for some of his legal cases, frequently involving railroads.
The collection also contains essays; poetry; the 1829 diary of Susannah Caroline Warwick on a trip from Virginia to Saratoga Springs, N.Y.; some genealogical material; printed ephemera; photographs; and copies of letters from Robert E. Lee, Jeb Stuart, and Jefferson Davis.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1816-1842, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1843-1844, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Sarah A. Daniel (Mrs. William Daniel, Jr.) 1841-1845 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: William Daniel, Jr., and Sarah Ann Warwick Daniel n.d. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1845-1862, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Letters bound into scrapbook by Daniel 1861-1865, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1863-1864 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1865-1884, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Letters bound by Daniel re Lee oration, (A-Z) 1883, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Letters bound by Daniel, "Letters of Congratulations sent to Maj. John W. Daniel, M.C. upon his election to the Senate," (A-R) 1885, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Letters bound by Daniel, "Letters of Congratulations sent to Maj. John W. Daniel, M.C., upon his election to the Senate," (S-Z) 1885 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1885-1893, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1894-1901, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1902-1905 Jun, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence 1905 Jul-1907, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - Correspondence 1907 Apr-1936, n.d., 5 folders (Box 9)
- Series II. Commonplace Books/Diaries
  - Autograph album of Sarah Warwick Daniel 1831-1837 (Box 9)
  - Commonplace books of John W. Daniel 1857-1863, 1865, 1867-1869, 3 items (Box 10)
  - Diaries of John W. Daniel 1903-1905, 1907, 4 items (Box 10)
  - Notebook of Edward M. Daniel 1935 (Box 10)
- Series III. Speeches: Senate, Political, General, Drafts and Research Material
  - Speeches: Senate -- Political affairs ca. 1887 (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate --"Excessive Taxation, and its Evils and its Remedy" 1888 (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "States Rights: The Source of the Domestic Tranquility We Now Enjoy" 1889 Feb 23 (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Race Relations 1889 (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "Senators from Montana" 1890 Apr 15 (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Sherman Silver Bill ca. 1890-1891 (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Taxing Powers 1892 Jul 20, 21 (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Panic of 1893 1893 (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Silver Demonetization 1893 (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate -- The Silver Question 1893 (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate -- On Repeal of Sherman Silver Purchase Acts ca. 1893-1894 (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Venezuela Boundary Dispute ca. 1884 (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Hawaiian Revolution 1894, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Hawaiian Revolution 1894 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "War Against Colombia" ca. 1895 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "Right and Duty of Congress to Recognize War in Cuba" 1897 May 17 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Recognition of Cuban Belligerency ca. 1897 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "The Public Faith" 1898 Jan 26, 27 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Presentation of a Portrait of Pocohontas 1899 Feb 28 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Philippines 1899 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "The Future of the United States and its Capital" 1900 Dec 12 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "John J. Ingalls" 1900 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "John Marshall" 1901 Feb 4 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Merchant Marine 1901 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Marcus Alonzo Hanna 1904 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "Matthew S. Quay" 1905 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "Fortifications Appropriation Bill and the Smokeless-Powder Trust" 1906 Mar 23 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Remarks on Third International Conference of American States (1906) 1906 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Brownsville Affair ca. 1906 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "Redfield Proctor" 1908 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "Morgan and Pettus" 1908 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Presentation to Vice-President Charles W. Fairbanks 1909 Mar 3 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "The Tax on Chesnut and Quebracho Tanning Extracts" 1909 May 20 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "Protection" 1909 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- "William B. Allison" 1909 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Tariff Bill 1909 (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Money Question n.d. (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Senate -- Sugar Tariff n.d. (Box 12)
  - Speeches: Political -- Campaign of 1873 1873 Sep 26 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Competition of the Republican Party under the Grant Administration 1876 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Testimony about Bank tax 1878 Apr 8 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- "The Financial Crisis, and How to Deal With It" 1878 Mar 11 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Election of 1880 1880 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Virginia Democratic Party 1880 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Congressional Elections of 1882 1882 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- John C. Calhoun and Internal Improvements 1883 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Acceptance of Democratic Nomination for U.S. House of Representatives, Sixth District (Va.) 1884 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Election to the U.S. Senate 1885 Dec (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- "Allen G. Thurman" (Secondary speech, 1888 Democratic National Convention) 1888 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- The Democratic Party 1892 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Depression of 1893 1893 Aug 17 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Silver at the 1896 Democratic Convention 1896 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Virginia Constitutional Convention 1902 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Virginia Democratic Primary for Senator ca. 1908-1910 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- "Reasons Why Bryan Should Be Elected" n.d. (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Defeat of William Jennings Bryan n.d. (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- The Democratic Party and Taxation n.d. (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Immigration n.d. (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- "Thieves Among the Freedmen" n.d. (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- William Mahone n.d. (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Virginia Debt Controversy n.d. (Box 13)
  - Speeches: Political -- Loose pages and outlines, Miscellaneous Topics n.d. (Box 13)
  - Speeches: General -- "Oration on the Illustrious Dead" 1859 Jun 28 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: General -- "American Literature, Its Growth" 1860 Jun 26 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: General -- "The People" 1866 Jun 28 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: General -- Gettysburg 1875 Oct 29 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: General -- "Conquered Nations" 1877 Jun 25 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: General -- "The End of the Centennial" (Kings Mountain, S.C.) 1880 Oct 6 (Box 13)
  - Speeches: General -- "Robert E. Lee" (delivered at unveiling of Lee statue, Lexington, Va.) 1883 Jun 28 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- Independence Day Speech 1884 Jul 4 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- "Washington" (delivered at dedication of Washington Monument) 1885 Feb 21 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- "Stonewall Jackson" 1888 Jun 13 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- "Marietta [Ohio]" 1888 Jul 28 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- 100th Anniversary of the U.S.A. 1889 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- "The Federal System" n.d. [1889?] (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- "Jefferson Davis" 1890 Jan 25 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- Memorial Day Observation at Norfolk, Va. 1891 Jun 4 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- "The Strategy of Providence" 1891 Jul 4 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- Speech at Confederate Reunion 1892 Apr 9 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- "Thomas Jefferson" 1893 Apr 13 & 1896 Apr 14 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- "The People and the Republic" 1893 Aug 9 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- Riverton Bridge 1894 May 1 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- "Mary Washington" and research material and program 1894 May 10 (Box 14)
  - Speeches: General -- "Jubal Early," (newspaper clipping) 1894 Dec 13 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "Americanism" 1895 [May 30?] (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "Monroe Doctrine" 1895 [May 30?] (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "Business" 1895 Aug 30 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- Cuba ca. 1895-1897 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- Outlines and Parts of Speeches on the Civil War 1897-1908 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- Cuba 1897 Jun 27 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- Independence Day 1897 Jul 5 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "Local Institutions" 1897 Oct 28 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "Abraham Lincoln" 1898 Feb 12 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "George Washington" 1899 Feb 22 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "Masonry" 1901 Jul 18 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "Good Roads" 1902 Mar 6 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "The Work of the Constitutional Convention" 1902 Aug 5-7 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- The Elks of Bedford, Va. 1903 May 21 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "The Unities of the Union" 1903 Dec 10 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "Our Mother Virginia" 1903 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "George Frisbee Hoar" 1904 Apr 19 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- Confederate Reunion at Lynchburg, Va. 1904 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "Ulysses S. Grant" 1905 Apr 27 (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- "McKinley" 1906 Sep 14, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Speeches: General -- Confederate Veterans 1907 (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- American Citizenship 1908 Jan 22 (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- "Protective Travelers Association" 1909 Sep 30 (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- American Government n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- "Aristocracy of True Worth" n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- Chicago Exposition n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- Confederate Memorial Day, Richmond, Va. n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- Democracy n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- "Everyone is the Son of His Own Work" n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- Parts of a Speech on History n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- "History of the English-Speaking People" n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- "Invention" n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- "John B. Minor" n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- The Judiciary n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- Labor n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- "No Recruits for the Old Confederates" n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- Railroads n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- Telephone Rates n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- "The Bright Side of the Age We Live In" n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- "The New South ..." n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- "The New Senate" n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- "Virginia Artillery" n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- Scattered Sheets n.d. (Box 16)
  - Speeches: General -- Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 17)
  - Speeches: Research material re Drafts of Speeches on Silver Coinage [ca. 1890-1896] (Box 17)
  - Speeches: Research material re Drafts of Speech(es) on Anglo-American Arbitration Treaty ca. 1897 (Box 17)
  - Speeches: Research material re Civil War 1902-1903, n.d. (Box 17)
  - Speeches: Research material re Railroad Rates 1906, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Speeches: Research material re Democratic Party and Territorial Expansion n.d. (Box 17)
  - Speeches: Research material re 14th Amendment n.d. (Box 17)
  - Speeches: Research material re Puerto Rico Dingley Tariff n.d. (Box 17)
  - Speeches: Research material re Attack on Theodore Roosevelt and Panama Canal n.d. (Box 17)
  - Speeches: Research material re Spanish-American War ca. 1897-1898 (Box 17)
  - Speeches: Research material re Tariff n.d. (Box 17)
  - Speeches: Research material re Taxation n.d. (Box 17)
  - Speeches: Research material re Trusts n.d. (Box 17)
- Series IV. Political Papers
  - Political Papers: Resolution on the Electoral Commission of 1877 1877 (Box 17)
  - Political Papers: Testimony on Charge that Daniel Bribed Black Voters in 1879 State Election 1879 (Box 17)
  - Political Papers: "The Debt Question" ca. 1881-1884 (Box 17)
  - Political Papers: Draft of 1896 Virginia Democratic Platform 1896 (Box 17)
  - Political Papers: Notes on the 1901 Virginia Constitutional Convention 1901 (Box 17)
  - Political Papers: Suffrage Provisions in 1902 Virginia Constitution ca. 1901-1902 (Box 17)
  - Political Papers: Notes for Democratic Party Platform 1904 (Box 18)
  - Political Papers: Notes re Practice of Cloture n.d. (Box 18)
  - Political Papers: Transcript of Debate in Virginia State Senate n.d. (Box 18)
  - Political Papers: "Reasons Given Why You Should Not Vote for the Democrats" n.d. (Box 18)
- Series V. Legal Papers
  - Legal Papers: Burkholders & Co. v. Francis Bell ca. 1873-1874 (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers: Fitzgerald v. City of Lynchburg, Va. 1876 (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers: Knight v. Johnson 1876 (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers: R. H. Pannill Case 1895 Sep 16 (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers: Williams v. McCall 1900-1901 (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers: Interstate Commerce Commission v. Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Co. and New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad Co. 1903 Dec 2 (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers: State Corporation Commission of Virginia 1909 (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers: Bell v. Kelly n.d. (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers: City of Lynchburg v. Norfolk & Western Railroad n.d. (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers: Halsey v. Jones n.d. (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers: Daniel heirs n.d., 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers: Halsey v. Jones n.d., 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Legal Papers: Jones Will Case n.d. (Box 19)
  - Legal Papers: Marbans Case n.d. (Box 19)
  - Legal Papers: Railroad Rate Case n.d. (Box 19)
  - Legal Papers: Retention of Carney Island n.d. (Box 19)
  - Legal Papers: Richmond and Allegheney Railroad Co. n.d. (Box 19)
  - Legal Papers: Shipman v. Fletcher n.d. (Box 19)
  - Legal Papers: EHS Case n.d. (Box 19)
  - Legal Papers: Miscellaneous n.d., 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Legal notebook re Johns Will Case 1902-1903 (Box 20)
  - Legal notebook of John S. Daniel 1865 Oct 25 (Box 20)
- Series VI. Essays and Poetry
  - Essays: "Stonewall Jackson" 1868 (Box 20)
  - Essays: Introduction to John Goode's Civilian Chieftains of the Confederacy 1909 (Box 20)
  - Essays: Notes for Reply to Criticism of Negotiable Instruments n.d. (Box 20)
  - Essays: Spanish American War n.d. (Box 20)
  - Essays: Tennyson and Shakespeare n.d. (Box 20)
  - Poetry n.d., 3 folders (Box 20)
- Series VII. Research Material
  - Civil War Material: Antietam, 17 Sep 1862 1899-1906, n.d. (Box 21)
  - Civil War Material: Appomattox, 9 Apr 1865 1886-1904, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Civil War Material: Big Bethel, 10 Jun 1861 1905, n.d. (Box 21)
  - Civil War Material: Cedar Creek, 19 Oct 1864 1904-1908, n.d., 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Civil War Material: Cedar Creek, 19 Oct 1864 n.d., 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: Cedar Mountain and Second Bull Run, 9 Aug - 1 Sep 1862 1904-1905 (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: Chambersburg, 30 Jul 1864 n.d. (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: Chancellorsville, 28 Apr - 6 May 1863 1907, n.d. (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: Confederate Infantry 1904-1909 (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: Confederate Military Records ca. 1900-1908 (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: Confederate Veteran Affairs 1891-1907 (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: John W. Daniel, C.S.A. (1842-1910) 1904-1908, n.d. (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: President Jefferson David, C.S.A. (1808-1889) 1908, n.d. (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: Brigadier General James Dearing, C.S.A. (1840-1865) n.d. (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: Early's Valley Campaign, 1864 1895-1906, n.d. (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: First Bull Run, 21 Jul 1861 1904-1905 (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: Five Forks, 1 Apr 1865 1880 (Box 22)
  - Civil War Material: Gettysburg Campaign, 9 Jun - 2 Jul 1863 1886-1906 (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: Gettysburg, 3 Jul 1863 ("Pickett's Charge") 1903-1905, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: Lt. General John B. Gordon, C.S.A. (1832-1904) n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: Lt. General Ulysses S. Grant, U.S.A. (1822-1889) n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: Lt. General Thomas J. "Stonewall" Jackson, C.S.A. (1824-1863) 1904-1906, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: Brigadier General William "Grumble" Jones, C.S.A. (1824-1864) n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: Major General W. H. F. Lee, C.S.A. (1837-1891) n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: General Robert E. Lee, C.S.A. (1807-1870) 1904, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: Lt. General James Longstreet, C.S.A. (1821-1904) 1904, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: Lynchburg, 15-18 Jun 1864 1901-1905, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: Monuments 1905, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: North Carolina Troops n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: Petersburg, 1864-1865 1905, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: Spotsylvania, 8-21 May 1864 1904-1907 (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: Major General James Ewell Brown "Jeb" Stuart, C.S.A. (1833-1864) n.d. (Box 23)
  - Civil War Material: The Wilderness, 5 May 1864 1905-1907, n.d. (Box 24)
  - Civil War Material: The Wilderness, 5 May 1864 n.d. (Box 24)
  - Civil War Material: The Wilderness, 6 May 1864 1904-1905, n.d. (Box 24)
  - Civil War Material: Wilderness Campaign, 5 May-18 Jun 1864 n.d. (Box 24)
  - Civil War Material: Winchester, 19 Sep 1864 1906-1907, n.d. (Box 24)
  - Civil War Material: Maps n.d. (Box 24)
  - Civil War Material: Miscellaneous 1904-1906, n.d. (Box 24)
  - Civil War Material: Virginia Confederate Artillery Units ca. 1904-1906 (Box 24)